Guide to the World War I Pamphlet Collection 1901-1944 (bulk 1914-1919)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
- United States - Pro-Germany Propaganda (in English), 1910 and undated; Oscar, John C. The European War and American Sentiment Towards the Nations Engaged in It. N.p: n.p, 1910.; Stoddard, John L. An American to Americans: The Truth about Germany and the War in Europe. n. d. (part of the pamphlet is missing) (Box-folder 40/4)
- United States - Pro-Germany Propaganda (in English), 1914; Frobenius, Herman. Germany's Hour of Destiny. New York: The International Monthly, 1914. (2 copies); Bennett, James O'Donell. An Open Letter to Sir Arthur Doyle from James O'Donell Bennett. 1914. (Box-folder 40/5)
- United States - Pro-Germany Propaganda (in English), 1914-1915; Keifer, Joseph Warren. Experiences and Observations of the Present European War; A Paper Read Before the Ohio Commandery of the Loyal Legion, October 7, 1914. 1914.; Strauss, Albert Anselm. The Absolute Truth in Regard to the Causes of the European World War! New York: A.A. Strauss, 1914.; Current Misconceptions about the War. New York: The Fatherland Corporation, 1915.; England's Perfidy Exposed by Americans. 1914. (Box-folder 40/6)
- United States - Public Opinion/Rights of Expression (in English), 1914-1915; A German Letter. Gertrude Atherton Publishes her Friend's War Views. New York: The New York Times, 1914.; Hearst, William Randolph. Editorials Appearing in The Newspapers Published by William Randolph Hearst On the War in Europe and the Attitude of the United States.(New York): (The Mc. Connell Print. Co.), 1915. (Box OS 43)
- United States - Public Opinion/Rights of Expression (in English), 1915?-1916; Ridder, Herman. The War Situation from Day to Day: America's Lost Opportunity. Chicago: Staats Zeitung, 1915?; Cukor, Morris. True Loyalty: An Address at the Mass Meeting of American Citizens of Hungarian Origin at the Garden Theatre. New York City: 1916. (Box OS 44)
- United States - Public Opinion / Rights of Expression (in English), 1917-1918; A Body-Blow Summary of Facts. A Camouflage Attempted by Hearst Comes to Naught. New York: 1917.; American Union Against Militarism. Constitutional Rights in War-Time. Washington, D.C.: Civil Liberties Bureau of the American Union Against Militarism, 1917. (2 copies; 1st and 2nd edition); Paine, Robert Treat. An Open Letter to the President of the United States. Boston?: s.n, 1918. (Box-folder 40/7)
- United States - Public Opinion: American-Germans as alien enemies (in English), 1917; Rathom, John R. Speech of John R. Rathom, Editor and Manager of the Providence Journal, Delivered at the Annual Dinner of the Traffic Club of Chicago ...: The German Intrigue against the United States. Chicago, Ill: The Club, 1917. (Box-folder 40/8)
- United State - Public Opinion: American-German Sentiment (in English), 1915; Viereck, G. S. & Chesterton, C. The Viereck-Chesterton Debate on "Whether the cause of Germany or that of the Allied Powers is Just". New York City: The Fatherland Corporation, 1915.; Mueller, Oscar C. Teuton or Slav? S.l: s.n, 1915.; Nagel, Charles. Neutrality and Public Opinion: An Address Delivered at Sheldon Memorial Hall, St. Louis, Mo. New York: Southard & Brown, 1915. (2 copies); The Committee for Investigation and Signatures. A Protest and a Decision. 1915. (Box-folder 40/9)
- United State - Public Opinion: American-German Sentiment (in English), 1916-1919; Kahn, Otto Hermann. Prussianized Germany: Americans of Foreign Descent and America's Cause. Chicago: Union League Club, 1917. (2 copies); Scherer, James A. B. The Confession of a De-Hyphenated American. New York: The New York Times, 1916. (2 copies); Mandl, J. Report of "On the Battlefield - Reminiscenses of a Soldier.". 1919. [(two page letter offering edits for the book "On the Battlefield..." written by an ex-German soldier who fled to America) (extremely fragile)] (Box-folder 40/10)
- United State - Public Opinion: American-German Sentiment (in German), 1916-1918; Charles, Heinrich. Die Deutschen Kriegsanleihen. [an Appeal to German-Americans.]. New York, 1916.; Committee on Public Information. Amerikanische bürgertreue von bürgern deutscher abkunft. Washington: G.P.O., 1917.; Kuehnemann, Eugen. Deutsch-Amerika Und Der Wiederaufbau Deutschlands Nach Dem Kriege. New York: Ostpreussenhilfe, 1918. (Box-folder 40/11)
- United States - Public Opinion: American-German Treatment (in English), 1918; Storey, Moorfield. The Right Ethical Attitude of the American People towards the German People. Storey, Weld & Co., 1918. (Box-folder 40/12)
- United States - Race Development Concerns (in English), 1918; Clymer, R. Swinburne. The Coming Conflict: Race Suicide, Polygamy or Higher Race Development-Which? Quakertown, Pa.: The Rosicrucian Aid, 1918. (2 copies) (Box-folder 40/13)
- United States - Racism (in English), 1914-1921; Smith, Franklin Orion. Stop the War - Prepare the Way for Italo-American Mediation-Union of White Race and Universal Peace. Speech of Hon. Frank O. Smith of Maryland in the House of Representatives. Washington: 1914.; American Legion. The American Legion's Answer to the Horror on the Rhine Mass Meeting of February 28, 1921. Speeches Delivered at the "All-American" Mass Meeting in Madison Square Garden, New York City, Friday Evening, March 18, 1921. New York City: American Campaign Against the Horror on the Rhine, 1921. (Box-folder 40/14)
- United States - Reconstruction (in English), 1917; After the War. The Following Statement is issued by The Georgia Land Owners' Association. Manufacturers Record, 1917. (Box OS 43)
- United States - Reconstruction (in English), 1919 and undated; Cross, Wilton Edson. The Problem of the Near East. New Hampshire: Congregational Unitarian Society, n. d.; Frank, Glenn, et al. A League of Nations. Vol. 4, No. 2. Boston: The National Economic League, 1919. (Box-folder 40/15)
- United States - Reconstruction (in English), 1925-1939; Manning, William Thomas, Nicholas Murray Butler, and John William Davis. Addresses at the Service of Thanksgiving for the Signing of the Treaties of Locarno and in the Interest of International Peace Held at the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, New York, December 13, 1925. [s.l.]: [s.n.], 1925.; National Catholic War Council (U.S.), Edward Mooney, and Joseph Schrembs. Bishop's Program of Social Reconstruction. Washington, D.C.: National Catholic welfare conference, 1939. (originally published in 1919) (Box 40/16)
- United States - Reconstruction: Socialism Argument (in English), 1917-1921; Nearing, Scott. The Menace of Militarism. New York: The Rand School of Social Science, 1917.; Nearing, Scott. The Great Madness: A Victory for the American Plutocracy. New York: The Rand School of Social Science, 1921. (Box-folder 40/17)
- United States - Reference Guides (in English), 1915; War-words: A Key to the Spelling, Pronunciation and Meaning of Many Terms Brought into Public Notice by the War. New York: Funk & Wagnalls, 1915. (40/18)
- United States - War Effort (in English), 1918-1920; Ways to Serve the Nation. Washington: Govt. Print. Off, 1918.; Cohen, Henry. About Twenty-Seven. New York: Public School 27 Welfare League, 1918.; Reilly, Frederick Joseph. The War History of Public School 33, the Bronx. New York: Charles Frances Press, 1920.; Mount Union High School (Huntingdon County, Pa.). Mount Union High School in the War. Mount Union, Pa: Times Printing House, 1920. (Box-folder 40/19)
- United States - War Effort: American Churches (in English), 1917 and undated; The National Service Commisssion of the Presbysterian Church, U. S. A. The Presbyterian Church & the War: 1917. Philadelphia: The Holmes Press, 1917.; The National Service Commisssion of the Presbysterian Church, U. S. A. The Presbyterian Church & the War: Bulletin No. 2, A Call to Prayer. New York City: 1917.; The National Service Commisssion of the Presbysterian Church, U. S. A. The Presbyterian Church & the War: Bulletin No. 3. New York City: 1917.; The National Service Commisssion of the Presbysterian Church, U. S. A. The Presbyterian Church & the War: Bulletin No. 4, Programs of Service for the Local Church. Philadelphia: The Holmes Press, 1917.; Seward, Roy Holland. What Is Real Democracy? Must It Be Attained to End War? New York: G.P. Putnam's sons, The Knickerbocker press, 1917.; Keates, W. J. R. The Cross from the Church of Revigny Speaks. New York: n. d.; Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America. The Duty of the Church in This Hour of National Need: A Message from the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, in Special Session Assembled at Washington, D.C., May 8 and 9, 1917. Washington, D.C.: [The Council, 1917. (2 copies) (Box-folder 41/1)
- United States - War Effort: American Churches (in English), 1918-1919; What the Pastors Say: Does our Campaign Help or Hurt? St. Louis, MO: Westminster College, 1918.; National Catholic War Council (Reprint from The Catholic Historical Review, Vol. IV). New York: 1918. (2 copies); Odell, Joseph H. Peter Sat by the Fire Warming Himself. Boston: The Atlantic monthly co.,], 1918.; Warburg, Paul M. How Can the Clergy Help the Victory Liberty Loan? Some Thoughts Respectfully Suggested by Paul M. Warburg in an Address Delivered Before the Ministerial Union in Baltimore, April 15th, 1919. 1919. (2 copies) (Box-folder 41/2)
- United States - War Effort: American Churches (in Swedish), 1917; Coleman, George W. and J. B. Gambrell. De Amerikanska Baptisternas Svar Till Baptisterna I Storbritannien Och Irland. London: Hayman, Christry & Lilly, Ltd., 1917. (The American Baptists' reposonse to Baptists in Britain and Ireland) (Box-folder 41/3)
- United States - War Effort Recognition (in English), 1918-1924; U.S. Playing Card Co. Dedicated to Our Boys Who Have Gone to the Front in the Cause of Humanity, Liberty and Justice: Roll of Honor of the U.S. Playing Card Co. S.l: s.n, 1918.; Virginia War History Commission, and Arthur Kyle Davis. Publications of the Virginia War History Commission: Extract from Source Volume II. Virginia War History in Newspaper Clippings. Richmond, Va: The Executive Committee, 1924.; Massachusetts General Hospital. Reception to the Massachusetts General Hospital Physicians, Nurses, and Employees Who Served in the Great War, June 9, 1919. Cambridge, [Mass.]: University Press, 1920.; Speyer, James. Address when presenting a Special Memorial Medal to the Physicians, Surgeons and Nurses of the Mount Sinai Hospital Unit for Patriotic Services during the War. New York: 1920.; The Pennsylvania War History Commission. State's Newspapers Gave Invaluable War Service. Vol. 1, No. 10. Philadelphia, PA: The Pennsylvania War History Commission, 1920. (typed news bulletin accompanied by a letter discussing the influence of newspapers during the war) (Box-folder 41/4)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications (in English), 1916-1919 and undated; The American Rights Committee. Bulletin No. 8. New York: The American Rights Committee, 1916.; Abbott, John M. "C'est La Guerre" April 6, 1917, November 11, 1918: Roster, Charleston Division, the Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company of West Virginia. Charleston, W. Va: Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company of West Virginia, 1919.; Wingate, George W. Victory Hall: Letter to the Mayor's Committee on Permanent Memorial for the Soldiers and Sailors from General George W. Wingate. 1919.; Stevenson, Christine Wetherill. Provision for Art, Music and Drama in Memorial Buildings. n. d. (typed letter/document); Letter. The Associated Survivors of the Sixth Army Corps of Washington D. C., n. d. (typed letter about a memorial to President Lincoln contributed by the Associated Survivors) (Box-folder 41/5)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications (in English), 1920-1930; Art and Executive Committee. New York City's War Memorial. New York: 1920.; Memorial Services in Honor of Members of the Baltimore Bar Killed in the World War. Baltimore: Press of The Daily Record, 1920.; Poore, B. A. Men and Officers of the 4th Division (Letter). Iowa: Association of the 4th Division, 1920.; The Burial of the Unknown Soldier, November 1921. Philidelphia: John Wanamaker, 1921. (includes President Harding's address and a sketch made at the time of the ceremony); Masten, Arthur H. Report of Results of Williams War Memorial Endowment Campaign. New York: 1922.; Tietze, J. No Man's Land. New York, 1924.; War Memorial Commission of the State of Maryland and City of Baltimore. The War Memorial, Baltimore, Maryland. [Baltimore, Md.]: War Memorial Commission of the State of Maryland and City of Baltimore, 1925.; Program of the Dedication of the Liberty Memorial. Kansas City, MO: 1926.; The Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society. Dedication of Ohio's World War Memorial: Program for the Unveiling of the Memorial to the Ohio Troops in the World War and Dedication of the New Wing of the Museum. Columbus, Ohio: 1926.; Illinois. Unveiling Ceremonies, Gold Star Mothers' Memorial at the Centennial Building. Springfield, Ill: Illinois Superintendent of Public Instruction, 1930. (Box-folder 41/6)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications: Soldiers' Lists (in English), undated; Soldiers and Sailors of West Liberty and Vicinity, World War 1917-1918. West Liberty: Index Printing Company, n. d.; American Companies for American Agents. Our First 147 Men in the World War. n. d. (Box-folder 41/7)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications: Soldiers' Lists (in English), 1918; Compliments of Major General Lejeune: Headquarters Second Division American Expeditionary Forces, France. Marine Corps Publicity Bureau, 1918.; Minnesota Almuni Weekly, Volume XVII, No. 2. Minneapolis: The General Lumni Association of the University of Minnesota, 1918. (Box-folder 41/8)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications: Soldiers' Lists (in English), 1920-1922; Dedication: Twenty-first Ward Memorial Monument, November 13 1920, Gorgas Park, Roxborough, Phila. Manayunk: Press of William H. Reichert & Co., 1920.; Hennepin County War Records Committee. World War Gold Star Roll of Hennepin County: Program and Exercises for the Dedication of Memorial Trees on the Victory Memorial Driveway. Minneapolis, Minn: Satterlee, Printing, 1921.; U. S. Marine Corps Club of St. Louis. They Have Not Died in Vain: First Annual Belleau Woods Day, Memorial Service. St. Louis, MO: 1922.; Eastern District High School. Unveiling of the Mural Painting, Dedicated to those who served in the World War, 1917-1918. New York: 1922. (Box-folder 41/9)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications: Soldiers' Lists (in English), 1923; Butler, William Allen Butler. Presentation of Memorial Tablet Containing the names of those who served their country during the World War and also name of members of the War Committee to The Lawyers Club. New York: Press of H. K. Brewer & Co., 1923.; Foreman, Edward R. Advance Sheets of World War Service Record of Rochester and Monroe County, New York: Volume 1, Those Who Died for Us. Rochester: City of Rochester, 1923. (Box-folder 41/10)
- United States - War Memorials / Dedications: Soldiers' Lists (in English), 1926-1928; Dedication of Municipal Auditorium. San Antonio, Texax: 1926.; National Committee for the Harvard War Memorial. The Harvard War Memorial. Boston: 1926. (2 copies); Smith, James C. History of the World War Memorial: Fort Wayne and Allen County, Their Tribute to the Glory of Their Sons, 1917-1918-1928. Fort Wayne, Ind: Hoosier Press, 1928. (Box-folder 41/11)
- United States - War Relief Effort (in English), 1916-1917 and undated; Brown-Landone. The Spirit of Belgium and France. Boston,; Children of America's Fund. Slowly Starving to Death! Boston, Mass: Children of America's Army of Relief, n. d.; American Welfare Association for German Children. An Appeal. Chicago: n. d.; War Relief Clearing House for France and Her Allies. Bulletin No. 160. New York: The Clearing House, 1916.; War Relief Clearing House for France and Her Allies. Bulletin No. 163. New York: The Clearing House, 1916.; Childe, Cromwell. Directory of Organizations Comprising the Federal Council of the Allied War Charities and Co-Operating with It. New York: 1917. (Box-folder 41/12)
- United States - War Relief Effort: American Red Cross (in English), 1916-1917 and undated; American Red Cross. When You Get Home. n. d.; American Red Cross. Home Service Section: The Link Between the Soldier Abroad and His Home in America. n. d.; De Schweinitz, Karl. This Side the Trenches, With the American Red Cross. New York: Printed by D. C. McMurtrie, 1917.; Kellogg, Paul Underwood. Seven weeks in Italy, the response of the American Red cross to the emergency. Paris: Office of the commissioner for Europe, 1917.; Norton, Richard. At Field Headquarters, France. Dear Morrison. London: Hudson & Kearns, Ltd., 1917.; Morrison, H. D. To Our Friends and Subscribers. London: American Volunteer Motor Ambulance Corps, 1916. (Box-folder 41/13)
- United States - War Relief Effort: American Red Cross (in English), 1918; McMurtrie, Douglas C. Reconstructing the Crippled Soldier. New York: Red Cross Institute for Crippled and Disabled Men, 1918.; Winston, Robert W. The Red Cross and the War. [Chapel Hill, N.C.]: Academic Affairs Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1918.; American Fund for French Wounded. Weekly Bulletin, Vol. 1, No. 35, July 21, 1918. Herbert Clarke, 1918. (Box-folder 41/14)
- United States - War Relief Effort: American Red Cross (in French), 1919; Le Messager: La Croix-Rouge Americaine en France. Paris: Draeger, 1919. (Box-folder 41/15)
- United States - War Relief Effort: Education/Rehabilitation (in English), 1918; United States. Hey There, Buddy! Washington, D.C.: U.S. G.P.O., 1918.; United States. To the Sweethearts, Sisters, Wives, and Mothers of Discharged Soldiers and Sailors. Washington, D.C.: U.S. G.P.O., 1918. (Box-folder 41/16)
- United States - War Relief Effort: Prisoners of War (POWs) (in English), 1916; Gospel Committee for Work Among War Prisoners. Dear Friend (letter). New York City: 1916. (Box-folder 41/17)
- United States - War Relief Effort: Wounded / Crippled (in English), 1915-1917 and undated; The Absolute Truth. n. d. (picture book of wounded and dead soldiers); Rockefeller Foundation. The Work of the Rockefeller Foundation's War Relief Commission. New York: (Rockefeller Foundation), 1915.; Hogg, Albert Nelson. What Other Nations Have Done to Help Their Disabled Soldiers and Sailors. Philadelphia: Corn Excange National Bank, 1917.; Holt, Winifred. A Report to the Committee for Men Blinded in Battle. [New York]: Committee for men blinded in battle, 1917. (Box-folder 42/1)
- United States - War Relief Effort: Wounded / Crippled (in English), 1918-1925; United States. President Wilson's Message on Healing the Hurts of Our Wounded: And Provisions of the Federal Law for Performing This Great Social Service. Washington, D.C.: U.S. G.P.O., 1918.; American Poets' Ambulances in Italy. Report of the Chairman to Contributors to the General Committee, and to the Public. New York: 1918.; Elks War Relief Commission. To the Soldiers Friend Committee. New York: Elks War Relief Commission, 1919. (2 copies); Hogan, Nick L. Nick Hogan: His Own Story of His Fight for Justice for Disabled Veterans. New York: A. W. Bryce, 1925. (Box-folder 42/2)
- Yugoslavia - Atrocities Alleged: Against the Central Powers (in French), 1919; Nouvelles atrocités austro-allemandes commises envers les officiers et soldats yougoslaves au cours de l'année 1919: documents officiels. Paris: Imprimerie "Graphique", 1919. (Box-folder 42/3)
- Yugoslavia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in English), 1918-1919; Social-demokratska stranka Bosne i Hercegovine, Mijo Radosević, and Franjo Markić. Memorandum Addressed by the Jugoslav Socialists to the International Socialist Peace Conference in Stockholm. London: The Jugolsav workmen's association, 1918. (2 copies); Bureau de presse serbe, Geneva. Report of the Serbian Press-Bureau in Geneva, No. 20. Geneva: Review of the enemy Press and Yougoslav information, 1918.; Bureau de presse serbe, Geneva. Report of the Serbian Press-Bureau in Geneva, No. 21. Geneva: Review of the enemy Press and Yougoslav information, 1918.; Piĭnić. Report of a Yugoslav interned in Italy. Paris: Impr. "Graphique", 1919. (2 copies); Union of Jugoslav University Students for Dalmatia Split, and League of Dalmatian University Students. Italian and Jugoslav Dispute. Split [Yugoslavia]: Union of Jugoslav University Students for Dalmatia Split, 1919. (2 copies) (Box-folder 42/4)
- Yugoslavia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in French), 1916-1919; Mémoire Supplémentaire sur la Question Yougoslave. [Paris, le 13 Mars 1916. Pour le Comité Yougoslave, le Président A.Trumbić.] Confidentiel. [Paris]: [Imp. Des Beaux-Arts], 1916.; Palaček, Ivan. Manifestations yougoslaves contre l'imperialisme italien. Paris: Graphique, 1919.; The New Europe. L'Italie, la Yougoslavie et le traité secret de Londres. Paris: Lang, Blanchong et Cie, 1919.; Bureau de presse yougoslave (Paris, France). Informations & documents. no. 46, mardi, 15 Avril 1919: Les Mensonges Ehontes de l'Agence Stefani. Paris: s.n, 1919.; Bureau de presse yougoslave (Paris, France). Informations & documents. no. 57, lundi, 28 Avril 1919: l'Expose de M. Zolger Relativement a La Frontiere Septentrionale du Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes. Paris: s.n, 1919.; Bureau de presse yougoslave (Paris, France). Informations & documents. no. 58, mardi, 29 Avril 1919: A l'Assemblee Yougoslave de Belgrade. Paris: s.n, 1919.; France. Bulletin Yougoslave, 20 Fevrier 1919, No. 17. Geneve: Informations yougoslaves, 1919. (Box-folder 42/5)
- Yugoslavia - Foreign Politics: Territory Questions (in French), 1919; Mémorandum présenté par les Slovènes du pays de Gorice au Conseil national de Ljubljana. Liubliana: [s.n.], 1919. (2 copies); Fabjancic, Vladislav, Antoinwe Lusin, and Dr. Matej Smalc. Lettre ouverte 'a monsieur le Président des Etats-Unis Woodrow Wilson. Gen'eve, le 8 Avril 1919. Geneve: Délégués du Conseil National de Ljubljana, 1919. (Box-folder 42/6)
- Yugoslavia - Foreign Politics: Territory Questions (in Slovenian), 1919; Carantanus. Jugoslavija in njene meje. V Ljubljani: Pisarna za Zasedeno Ozemlje, 1919. (Box-folder 42/7)
- Yugoslavia - Military (in French), 1919; Edition du Bulletin Yougoslave. Les marins yougoslaves. Leur role dans la lutte pour l'indépendance de la Yougoslavie et pour le triomphe du Droit et de la Justice. Gen'eve: E. Chaulmontet, 1919.; Comment s'Opéra: L'Écroulement du Front Austro-Hongrois. Paris: Comité Yugoslave, 1919. (Box-folder 42/8)